A Finding Aid to the Dwan Gallery Records, 1959-circa 1982, bulk 1959-1971, in the Archives of American Art AAA.dwangall
Archives of American Art
Dwan Gallery records
bulk 1959-1971
1959-circa 1982
AAA.dwangall
Archives of American Art
2.3 Linear feet
The Dwan Gallery records measure 2.3 linear feet and consist primarily of files of exhibitions curated by Virginia Dwan at Dwan Galleries in Los Angeles (1959-1967) and New York (1965-1971). Found within this nearly comprehensive set of exhibition files may be lists of exhibited works, price lists, photographs, slides or color transparencies of installations, invitations, full-size posters, magazine and newspaper clippings and exhibition catalogs.
Dwan Gallery
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Dwan Gallery records were donated in 1996 by Virginia Dwan, the former owner of the gallery.
Separated Materials note
Dwan Gallery exhibition catalogs that were donated to the Archives in 1989 were transferred to the Smithsonian Institution American Art and National Portrait Gallery Library.
Bard College's Center for Curatorial Studies and Art in Contemporary Culture holds Dwan Gallery materials related to exhibitions in the Library and Archives.
Related Archival Materials note
Also found within the Archives of American Art is an interview with Virginia Dwan conducted March 21 through June 1, 1984 by Charles Stuckey.
Existence and Location of Copies note
The collection was digitized in its entirety in 2013 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
In 1959, Virginia Dwan opened her first gallery on 1091 Broxton Avenue in the Westwood Village neighborhood of Los Angeles, California. Her independent wealth allowed her to open a gallery without worrying about business and sales. Three years after opening, the Dwan Gallery moved into a new Westwood Village space especially designed to express the gallery's contemporary aesthetic. In 1965, Virginia Dwan moved to New York City and founded an east coast branch of the Dwan Gallery at 29 West 57th Street.
Early exhibitions at the Dwan Gallery showed Abstract Expressionist artists and works of art from New York which Dwan consigned from other galleries. After traveling to New York and France, Virginia Dwan's interests and tastes manifested in exhibitions by 1961 with Yves Klein. Through Klein, Dwan made connections to other Nouveaux Réalistes artists that the gallery featured in solo and group shows. Later exhibitions featured Land and Minimilist artists. Dwan recognized that many of her shows were not considered salable but continued to show the avant-garde. She saw the gallery as an opportunity to expose the public to different styles of art.
Virginia Dwan maintained a close and personal relationship with many of her artists. She allowed large stipends to gallery artists and invited them to spend time at her home in Malibu, California. When working with artists concentrating on found objects, Dwan would accompany them on scavenger hunts and shopping trips. In the case of Robert Smithson and other Land Art artists, she traveled to offsite locations to visit works of art in progress. Dwan relied on her longtime gallery director, John Weber to interact with collectors as she preferred to maintain her connection with the artists.
The Dwan Gallery Los Angeles closed in mid-1967 but the New York branch remained open. By 1971, Virginia Dwan felt pressure to support her thirteen artists through a period of economic insecurity. She decided to close the gallery secretly and only informed her artists at the last minute. The final exhibition at Dwan Gallery New York closed in June of 1971.
Scope and Contents note
The Dwan Gallery records measure 2.3 linear feet and consist primarily of files of exhibitions curated by Virginia Dwan at Dwan Galleries in Los Angeles (1959-1967) and New York (1965-1971). Found within this nearly comprehensive set of exhibition files may be lists of exhibited works, price lists, photographs, slides or color transparencies of installations, invitations, full-size posters, magazine and newspaper clippings and exhibition catalogs.
Artists that held exhibitions at the Dwan Gallery in New York and Los Angeles include: Robert Goodnough, Robert Richenburg, Larry Rivers, Philip Guston, Yves Klein, Salvatore Scarpitta, Arakawa, Martial Raysse, Ad Reinhardt, Arman, Franz Kline, Edward Kienholz, Claes Oldenburg, Niki de Sainte Phalle, Joan Mitchell, Robert Rauschenberg, Robert Morris, Dan Flavin, Raymond Parker, Kenneth Snelson, Carl Andre, Sol LeWitt, Robert Smithson, and Anastasi. Also, the exhibition files are nearly comprehensive and include: Language to be Looked at and/or Things to be Read annual series (1967-1970), Boxes (1964), Earth Works (1968), My Country 'tis of Thee (1962) and 10 (1967 and 1968). Many of the multiple artist shows were created and organized by gallery director John Weber and/or Virginia Dwan. Many of these exhibition files include full-sized posters and panoramic photos showing installations.
Also found are records created by a consulting firm hired by the Dwan Gallery to inventory the exhibition files prior to donation to the Archives of American Art. These guides appear at the beginning of each series and outline a chronology of exhibitions held at each branch.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged into two series:
Series 1: Los Angeles Exhibition Files, 1959-1967, after 1981 (Box 1-2, 5, OV6, OV8; 1.3 linear feet)
Series 2: New York Exhibition Files, 1965-1971, after 1982 (Box 2-4, OV7; 1.0 linear feet)
Anastasi, William, 1933-; Andre, Carl, 1935-; Arakawa, Shusaku, 1936-; Arman, 1928-; Dwan Gallery (Los Angeles, Calif.); Dwan Gallery (New York, N.Y.); Dwan, Virginia; Flavin, Dan, 1933-; Goodnough, Robert, 1917-; Guston, Philip, 1913-; Kienholz, Edward, 1927-; Klein, Yves, 1928-1962; Kline, Franz, 1910-1962; Lewitt, Sol, 1928-; Mitchell, Joan, 1926-; Morris, Robert, 1931-; Oldenburg, Claes, 1929-; Parker, Raymond, 1922-; Rauschenberg, Robert, 1925-; Raysse, Martial, 1936-; Reinhardt, Ad, 1913-1967; Richenburg, Robert; Rivers, Larry, 1925-; Saint-Phalle, Niki de, 1930-; Scarpitta, Salvatore, 1919-; Smithson, Robert; Snelson, Kenneth, 1927-; Weber, John, 1932-; Abstract expressionism; Art galleries, Commercial--California--Los Angeles; Art galleries, Commercial--New York (State)--New York; Art--California--Los Angeles--Exhibitions; Art--New York (State)--New York--Exhibitions; Artists--United States; Earthworks (Art); Minimal art; Photographs; Slides (photographs)
- Los Angeles Exhibition Files, 1959-1965, after 1981; Series 1; 1.3 Linear feet Box 1-2, 5, OV6, OV8
  Scope and Contents note
  Found within this series may be lists of exhibited works, price lists, photographs, slides or color transparencies of installations, invitations, full-size posters, magazine and newspaper clippings and exhibition catalogs. Noteworthy exhibitions include artists Robert Goodnough, Raymond Parker, Yves Klein, Salvatore Scarpitta, Arakawa, Martial Raysse, Robert Rauschenberg, Niki de Sainte Phalle, Claes Oldenburg, Larry Rivers and Kenneth Snelson. Other important exhibitions include Boxes (1964), My Country 'tis of Thee (1962), and 10 (1967).
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged in chronological order according to the opening date of each exhibition. Exhibition posters and photos of installations were placed into oversized folders.
  Existence and Location of Copies note
  This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Guides to Los Angeles Exhibtions, after 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Stanley Twardowicz, 1959 October 19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Various Artists: Prints, 1959 November 17 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Drawings, Watercolors, Collages, 1959 December 12 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Matsumi Kanemitsu, 1960 January 19 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Reginald Pollack: Recent Paintings, 1960 February 9 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Friedel Dzubas, 1960 March 8 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Paul Brach, 1960 April 4 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Oversized material housed in OV6
  - Robert Goodnough, 1960 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Seymour Boardman: Paintings, 1960 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Harry Nadler, 1960 June 27 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 15 of New York, 1960 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Robert Richenburg, 1960 November 14 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Various Artists, 1960 December 19 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Stanley Twardowicz, 1961 January 9 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Stephen Pace, 1961 March 6 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Larry Rivers, 1961 February 6 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Franz Kline and Philip Guston, 1961 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Raymond Parker, 1961 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Yves Klein: Le Monochrome, 1961 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Salvatore Scarpitta, 1961 June 24 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Joan Mitchell, 1961 September 18 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Six Sculptors, 1961 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Matsumi Kanemitsu, 1961 November 13 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Robert Goodnough, 1962 January 27 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Ad Reinhardt, 1962 February 4 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Robert Rauschenberg, 1962 March 4 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - William Waldren, 1962 April 1 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Arman, 1962 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Various Artists, 1962 June 11 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Harry Nadler, 1962 July 9 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Various Artists, 1962 September 7 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Raymond Parker, 1962 October 7 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - My Country 'tis of Thee, 1962 November 18 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Matsumi Kanemitsu: Recent Paintings, 1962 December 16 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Martial Raysse, 1963 January 6 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Dealer's Choice, 1963 February 10 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Franz Kline: Memorial, Paintings 1950-1961, 1963 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Oversized material housed in OV8
  - Larry Rivers, 1963 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Jean Tinguely, 1963 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Edward Kienholz, 1963 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Claes Oldenburg, 1963 October 1 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Sven Lukin, 1963 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Ad Reinhardt: Recent Paintings, 1963 November 24 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Various Artists, 1963 December 29 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Niki de Sainte Phalle, 1964 January 5 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Boxes, 1964 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Oversized material housed in Box 5
  - William Waldren, 1964 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Arakawa: Diagrams, 1964 March 29 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Martial Raysse, 1964 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Oversized material housed in OV6, OV8
  - Gallery Artists, 1964 June 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - New York, New York, 1964 June 29 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Edward Kienholz: 3 Tableaux, 1964 September 29 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - James Rosenquist, 1964 October 27 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lucas Samaras, 1964 November 24 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Arena of Love, 1965 January 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Oldenburg, Whitman, Dine and Talbert, 1965 February 9 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Dakota Daley and Nicholas Quennell, 1965 March 16 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Robert Rauschenberg: Drawings, 1965 April 13 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Charles Frazier, 1965 May 11 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Various Artists, 1965 June 8 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Mark Di Suervo: Two Large Works, 1965 September 29 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Larry Rivers, 1965 November 16 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Various Artists, 1965 December 21 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Allen D'Archangelo, 1966 January 18 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Neil Williams, 1966 February 15 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Robert Morris: Sculpture, 1966 March 15 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Arakawa, 1966 May 10 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Various Artists, 1966 May 10 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Robert Grosvenor, 1966 April 12 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Summer Show, 1966 July 5 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Anthony Magar and Forrest Myers, 1966 October 4 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - David Novros: Five Paintings, 1966 November 1 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - John Chamberlain, 1966 November 29 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Kenneth Snelson, 1967 January 9 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - DWNY at DWLA, 1967 February 7 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Carl Andre: Cuts, 1967 March 8 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Sol LeWitt, 1967 April 4 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - 10, 1967 May 2 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Martial Raysse: Retrospective, 1967 June 31 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Oversized Boxes Catalog, 1964 February 2 (Box 5)
    Material scanned with Box 1, F47
  - Oversized Exhibition Posters, 1960-1967 (Box OV6)
    Material scanned with Box 1, F8, 12-13, 15, 19-21, 24, 43, 46, 48, 50 and Box 2, F9, 13, 16-18, 21-25, 27, 29
  - Oversized Photographs, 1963-1967 (Box OV8)
    Material scanned with Box 1, F38, 40, 44, 49-50 and Box 2, F2, 5-6, 8-9, 18-19, 23-24, 26, 30
- New York Exhibition Files, 1965-1971, after 1982; Series 2; 1 Linear feet Box 2-4, OV7
  Found within this series may be lists of exhibited works, price lists, photographs, slides or color transparencies of installations, invitations, full-size posters, magazine and newspaper clippings and exhibition catalogs. Noteworthy exhibitions include artists Arakawa, Anastasi, Kenneth Snelson, Sol LeWitt, Robert Smithson, Carl Andre, Dan Flavin, and Walter De Maria. Other important exhibitions include 10 (1966), Language to be Looked at and/or Things to be Read (1967-1970), and Earth Works (1968).
  This series is arranged in chronological order according to the opening date of each exhibition. Exhibition posters have been placed into oversized folders.
  - Guides to New York Exhibitions, after 1982 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Edward Kienholz: The Beanery, 1965 November 23 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Oversized material housed in OV7
  - Arakawa: For Instance, Instant, 1966 January 4 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Anastasi: Sound Object, 1966 February 1 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Tom Doyle, 1966 March 1 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Kenneth Snelson, 1966 April 12 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Sol LeWitt, 1966 May 10 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - 10, 1966 October 4 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Michael Steiner, 1966 November 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Robert Smithson, 1966 November 29 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Scale Models and Drawings, 1967 January 7 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Edward Kienholz: Concept Tableaux, 1967 February 4 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Richard Baringer, 1967 March 4 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - David Novros: Paintings, 1967 April 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Anastasi: Six Sites, 1967 April 29 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Language to be Looked at and/or Things to be Read, 1967 June 3 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Tim Doyle, 1967 October 7 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Arakawa, 1967 November 4 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Carl Andre: Periodic Table, 1967 December 2 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Kenneth Snelson, 1968 January 6 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Sol LeWitt: 46 3 Part Variations, 1968 February 3 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Robert Smithson, 1968 March 2 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Michael Steiner, 1968 March 30 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Charles Ross: Prisms, 1968 April 27 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Language II, 1968 May 25 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Earth Works, 1968 October 5 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Dan Flavin: Cool White, etc., 1968 November 2 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Erwin Heerich: Cardboard Sculpture, 1968 November 30 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Fred Sandback: Five Situations, 1969 January 4 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Robert Smithson: Lake Site-Nonsite, 1969 February 1 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Charles Ross: Prisms, 1969 March 1 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Walter De Maria: Bed of Spikes, 1969 March 29 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Carl Andre, 1969 April 26 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Language III, 1969 May 24 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Sol LeWitt: Wall Drawing, 1969 October 4 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Arakawa: Decisive Ending, 1969 November 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Dwan, 10 Years, 1969 November 29 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Michael Heizer: New York/ Nevada, 1970 January 10 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Dan Flavin: Cornered Installations, 1970 February 7 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Kenneth Snelson, 1970 March 7 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Fred Sandback, 1970 April 4 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Anastasi: Sculpture, 1970 May 2 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Anastasi: Continuum, 1970 May 16 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Language IV, 1970 June 2 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Richard Long: Sculpture, 1970 October 3 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Robert Smithson: Great Salt Lake, Utah, 1970 October 31 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Gallery Artists, 1970 November 28 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Charles Ross: Sunlight Dispersion, 1971 January 6 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Robert Ryman: Paintings, 1971 February 6 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Carl Andre, 1971 April 3 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Sol LeWitt: Paintings and Drawings, 1971 May 1 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Dan Flavin: to Barnett Newman, 1971 March 6 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Final Exhibition, Gallery Artists, 1971 June 1 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Oversized Exhibition Posters, 1965-1971 (Box OV7)
    Material scanned with Box 2, F32-36, 38, Box 3, F1-3, 5, 7, 10-12, 14-16, 21, 23, and Box 4, F3-4, 6-10, 13, 19